Guide to the Arlin Turner Papers, 1927-1980 RL.01312
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arlin Turner papers
1927-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Turner, Arlin
RL.01312
15.6 Linear Feet
The papers span Turner's career as a scholar of American literature, from his undergraduate education at West Texas State University in 1927 to his death in 1980, when he was an instructor at Southwest Texas State University. Comprised primarily of personal and professional correspondence with scholars and publishers of American literature, including Gay Wilson Allen, John Q. Anderson, Louis Budd, Robert Cantwell, James B. Colvert, Eddie Gay Cone, Benjamin Franklin Fisher, Albert Mordell, Norman Holmes Pearson, William Stafford, and Edmund Wilson. There are also letters, printed matter, reports, and minutes that Turner collected as a member or officer of organizations, including the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association, Committee for American Studies, and the Associated Research Council. The Turner Papers also document the development of high school, collegiate, and graduate level instruction in American literature through the organizational records and course materials, the latter of which include Turner's personal writings and research notes, subject files, clippings, lecture notes, and other printed materials on various authors or genres of American literature, including Southern literature, American humor, Nathaniel Hawthorne and George Washington Cable.
circa 9750 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection contains sensitive information. Patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Arlin Turner Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 1980, 1986, 1987, and 1996. Portions of this collection were transferred from Duke University Archives in 2002.
Biographical Note
Arlin Turner
1909 Born November 25 in Abilene, Tex.
1927 Received B.A. from West Texas State University
1930 Received M.A. from the University of Texas
1934 Received Ph.D. from the University of Texas
1934-1936 Instructor at the University of Texas
1936-1953 Professor of English at Louisiana State University
1941 Published Hawthorne as Editor
1942-1946 Served in U.S. Naval Reserve
1947-1948 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship
1951 Visiting Professor, University of Montreal. Visiting Professor, University of Colorado
1952 Awarded Fulbright appointment to University of Western Australia
1953-1979 Professor of English, Duke University
1956 Published George W. Cable: A Biography
1957 Visiting Professor, University of Texas
1958 Visiting Professor, University of Virginia
1958-1964 Chairman, Duke University Department of English
1959-1960 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship
1960 Published Mark Twain and George W. Cable: The Record of a Literary Friendship
1961 Visiting Professor, University of Illinois
1961 Published Nathaniel Hawthorne: An Introduction and Interpretation
1962 Visiting Professor, University of Iowa
1963 Visiting Professor, New York University
1964 Visiting Professor, University of Bombay
1966-1967 Awarded Fulbright appointment to University of Hull, Hull, England
1968 Visiting Professor, University of Pennsylvania
1969 Huntington Library Research Award
1973-1974 Awarded Senior Fellowship, National Endowment for the Humanities
1974 Awarded James B. Duke Professorship
1976 Received Doctor of Humane Letters from Berea College, Ky.
1978 Visiting Professor, State University of New York
1979 Appointed Therese Kayser Lindsey Professor of Literature, Southwest Texas State University
1980 Published Nathaniel Hawthorne, a biography.
1980 Died, April 24 in Austin, Tex.
Biographical/Historical note
Organizational Service Biography
The following lists selected offices and leadership roles held by Turner in professional organizations as documented in this collection. Turner was active in other professional groups that are not represented in his papers. The dates reflect the years of the highest positions he held and do not represent the total period of his membership or leadership. The organizations are listed alphabetically.
Chronology
1956-1967 Fellowship Selection Committee, 1961-1963, 1965-1966 American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) Regional Associate, 1956-1967
1954-1979 Managing Editor, 1954-1963 Editor, 1969-1979 American Literature
1955-1972 Advisory Council, 1955-1957, 1967-1972 Executive Committee, 1958-1959 American Studies Association (ASA) Vice President, 1969-1970
1956-1968 Member, Committee for American Studies 1956-1960, 1962-1963, 1967-1968 Committee for International Exchange of Persons, (CIEP), Conference Board of Associated Research Councils (CBC) Chairman, Committee for American Studies, 1957-1960
1949-1967 Modern Language Association (MLA) Chairman, American Literature Section, 1966-1967 Secretary, American Literature Section, 1949-1967
1961-1966 Director, Commission on Literature, 1964-1966 Director, 1961-1964 National Council of Teachers of English (NCTE)
1968-1976 Member, Advisory Panel on Media Programs, 1976 Chairman, Fellowship Selection Committee, 1968-1972 National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH)
1956-1957 South Atlantic Modern Language Association (SAMLA) Chairman, American Literature Section, 1956-1957
1956-1979 Member, Editorial Board 1956-1979 South Atlantic Quarterly
1955-1972 Southeastern American Studies Association (SEASA) Vice-President, 1955-1956, 1968-1970 President, 1956-1957, 1970-1972
Biographical/Historical note
Henry Arlin Turner, a professor of English and Literature, is best known for his scholarship on Nathaniel Hawthorne and George Washington Cable. His interests also included Edgar Allan Poe, Herman Melville, Mark Twain, William Faulkner, Southern Literature, and American Humor writings. Turner authored, edited, or reviewed an extensive list of publications on these subjects, in addition to the monographs listed above.
Collection Overview
The Arlin Turner Papers, 1927-1980, span Turner's entire career as a scholar of American literature, from his undergraduate education at West Texas State University in 1927 to his death in 1980, when he was an instructor at Southwest Texas State University. The Turner Papers are comprised primarily of personal and professional correspondence with scholars and publishers of American literature. The correspondence includes letters, printed matter, reports, and minutes that Turner collected as a member or officer of organizations to which many of these literary scholars belonged. These materials, in addition to the clippings, printed materials and other writings Turner collected, provide insight into the development of the profession of American literary scholarship in the 1920s and 1930s; demonstrate the major concerns, issues, conflicts, and interests of its practitioners over the following four decades; and record research advancements and contributions to scholarship on the literary figures of most interest to Turner. The Turner Papers also document the development of high school, collegiate, and graduate level instruction in American literature through the organizational records and course materials, the latter of which include Turner's personal writings and research notes, subject files he collected, clippings, lecture notes, and other printed materials on various authors or genres of American literature. Finally, this collection provides glimpses into Turner's personal career and scholarly thought through the writings which are included, both those he presented orally as speeches or lectures, or those he published as articles or books. The Turner Papers are organized into five series: Correspondence, Course Materials, Organizations, Printed Material, and Writings and Speeches.
A student of the first generation of American literature scholars in the 1920s, Turner played an important role in the network of scholarly exchange that was vital to the emergence of the discipline in the decades following. Turner kept in contact with numerous colleagues in colleges and universities across the United States and throughout the world, including many former graduate students who later became influential literary scholars and critics themselves. The Correspondence Series, 1930-1980, documents Turner's role in this network of scholarly exchange. The Individuals Subseries, 1930-1980, includes Turner's most voluminous correspondents: American literature specialists and authors Gay Wilson Allen, John Q. Anderson, Louis Budd, Robert Cantwell, James B. Colvert, Eddie Gay Cone, Benjamin Franklin Fisher, Albert Mordell, Norman Holmes Pearson, William Stafford, and Edmund Wilson. The Publications Subseries, 1934-1979, contains portions of Turner's communications with editors, publishers, and presses primarily regarding article reviews or manuscript evaluations of others' work. This subseries also contains some information concerning Turner's own articles, manuscripts, and various published works. Correspondence, brochures, press releases, reports, and contractual information concerning Turner's speaking engagements or attendance at professional meetings is collected in the Conferences, Speeches, and Lectures Subseries, 1961-1978 (bulk 1961-1964). Miscellaneous materials comprised primarily of letters arranged by subject are assembled in the Other Correspondence Subseries, 1948-1979 and undated This subseries also contains research notes, memos, and printed material. These papers document Turner's visiting professor appointments and awards, as well as his interest in topics such as the Duke University Library, the Huntington Library, George W. Cable primary sources, and international scholars of American Literature.
The Course Materials Series, undated, is comprised of information Turner collected to aid in composing classroom lectures, and other teaching materials. He maintained an extensive set of files on American authors, which can be found in the Lecture Notes, By Author Subseries, undated Most files contain a brief biography of the author and list of his major compositions, but may also include copies of their works, a typescript of Turner's lecture on the author, and related materials such as clippings or Turner's handwritten research notes. Turner also collected files on genres of literature, delineated both by region, such as Louisiana or British literature, or by style, such as Short Stories or Recent Fiction. These can be found in the Lecture Notes, By Subject Subseries, undated The Class Files Subseries, undated, contains Turner's teaching materials including syllabi, quizes, and exams. These files pertain to courses Turner taught (or in a few early instances, took) in subjects including American Literature before the Civil War, Post-Civil War Literature, Hawthorne and Melville, American Humor, and Southern Literature. Specific course numbers and titles have been provided wherever possible.
Arlin Turner was an active leader and participant in many of the organizations associated with his profession and interests, which are chronicled in the Organizations Series, 1929-1979 (bulk 1936-1979). These scholarly groups developed policies, conducted studies, and otherwise governed the profession. Thus, Turner's influential positions in most of these associations render his thorough collection of organizational records both valuable and useful. Folders in this series primarily contain correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, and printed matter such as newsletters, brochures, and clippings. Most notable is Turner's work with the Modern Language Association (MLA), whose American Literature Section members are primarily responsible for the spread of American Studies programs across the globe. Turner's records also document his work with the South Atlantic Modern Language Association (SAMLA), the American Studies Association (ASA), and the Southeastern American Studies Association (SEASA). This series likewise chronicles Turner's leadership roles in the National Council of Teachers of English (NCTE), the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) and the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH).
Turner was also a member of the Committee for American Studies, the advisory group for the Conference Board of Associated Research Councils' (CBC) Committee for International Exchange of Persons (CIEP). The Organizations Series also includes files on the selection of Fulbright Scholars that he collected as a member of that committee. In addition, Turner served as chairman of this committee during the period in which the Loewenberg controversy consumed the CIEP's affairs. When Prof. Bert J. Loewenberg was denied a Fulbright Award in 1959 despite the committee's recommendation, its members threatened to resign in protest against allegations that Loewenberg's past political activity was to blame. Thus, significant amounts of correspondence from fellow committee members Ray Billington, John Hope Franklin, Harvey Wish, and Charles Barker regarding the controversy is found in this series.
Arlin Turner accumulated a significant number of clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, reprints, and publications related to American Literature. These are collected in the Printed Material Series, undated Included in this series are materials from the Educational Testing Service (ETS), memorabilia from Turner's time at the University of Hull in England, literary magazines, and miscellaneous clippings primarily regarding Southern writers (especially North Carolina authors), William Faulkner, and the New Critics (a.k.a. The Fugitives).
The Writings and Speeches Series, 1938-1980 and undated (bulk 1964-1977), contains copies of Turner's significant oral presentations and other written work, both published and unpublished, in addition to some writings of other authors he accumulated. Files from Turner's speaking engagements include both correspondence and typed copies of his presentations. This series also contains unidentified speech notes and writings, in addition to a bound typescript with handwritten edits of Turner's Nathaniel Hawthorne: A biography. Writings about Turner, including obituaries, tributes, his curriculum vita and the like, are also found in the Writings and Speeches Series.
Fulbright scholarships; American wit and humor; College teachers -- Correspondence; American literature -- North Carolina; American literature -- Study and teaching; American literature -- 20th century -- History and criticism; American literature -- Louisiana; Authors, American; American literature -- 19th century -- History and criticism; American literature -- Southern States; Anderson, John Q.; American Studies Association; American Council of Learned Societies; Modern Language Association of America. American Literature Section; Allen, Gay Wilson, 1903-1995; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925; Budd, Louis J.; Billington, Ray Allen, 1903-1981; Barker, Charles A. (Charles Albro), 1904-; Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography; George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Mordell, Albert, 1885-; Louisiana State University (Baton Rouge, La.) -- Faculty; Louisiana State University (Baton Rouge, La.). Dept of English; Cone, Eddie Gay, 1938-; Conference Board of the Associated Research Councils. Committee on International Exchange of Persons. Committee on American Studies; Cantwell, Robert, 1908-; Colvert, James Brumley; Fisher, Benjamin Franklin; Duke University. Department of English -- Curricula; Duke University. Department of English -- Faculty; Wish, Harvey, 1909-; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009; National Endowment for the Humanities; National Council of Teachers of English; South Atlantic Modern Language Association; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Stafford, William, 1914-; Southeastern American Studies Association; Turner, Arlin
- Correspondence Series, 1930-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence Series has been organized into four subseries: Individuals; Publications; Conferences, Speeches, Lectures; and Other Correspondence. Only the first of these retains Turner's arrangement.
  - Individuals Subseries, [ca. 1930-1980]
    The Individuals Subseries is comprised of correspondence between Turner and other scholars in American literature, students and former students, and editors and publishers. Chief topics in the letters include recent research, manuscript evaluations, speaking engagements and conference attendance, personal updates, and occasional recommendations and peer reviews (SENSITIVE). To preserve original order, this subseries has been maintained as a discrete unit--arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name in the same way Turner kept the files. Consequently, there may be significant overlap with other correspondence subseries. For example, correspondence with a publisher may be filed by an editor or publisher's last name in this subseries or by the publication title or the press that produced it in the Publications Subseries.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    This subseries contains sensitive information (recommendations and peer reviews). Before using these materials, patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights. Contact Research Services staff for assistance.
    - Aaron, Dan (Box 1)
    - Adams, Hazard (Box 1)
    - Adams, Percy (Box 1)
    - Adams, Richard P. (Box 1)
    - Aderman, Ralph (Box 1)
    - Alexander, Margaret W. (Box 1)
    - Allen, Gay Wilson (Box 1)
    - Allen, Thomas J. (Box 1)
    - Altenbernd, Lynn (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Carl (Box 1)
    - Anderson, John Q. (Box 1)
    - Angyal, Andrew J. (Box 1)
    - Ano, Fumio (Box 1)
    - Appel, Benjamin (Box 1)
    - Applewhite, James (Box 1)
    - Arms, George (Box 1)
    - Arndt, Karl J.R. (Box 1)
    - Arvin, Newton (Box 1)
    - Asquith, Cynthia (Box 1)
    - Asselineau, Roger (Box 1)
    - Auchincloss, Louis (Box 1)
    - Axelsson, Arne (Box 1)
    - A Misc. (Box 1)
    - Baker, Carlos (Box 1)
    - Bandy, W. T. (Box 1)
    - Baym, Nina (Box 1)
    - Barber, Edwin (Box 1)
    - Barker, Charles (Box 1)
    - Barnes, Warner (Box 1)
    - Beach, Leonard B. (Box 1)
    - Bearden, Ethel (Box 1)
    - Beebe, Maurice (Box 1)
    - Belflower, Robert (Box 1)
    - Bell, Vereen (Box 1)
    - Benson, Carl (Box 1)
    - Bennett, Raymond (Box 1)
    - Bevington, Helen (Box 1)
    - Bickley, Bruce (Box 1)
    - Bier, Jesse (Box 1)
    - Billington, Ray (Box 1)
    - Blair, Walter (Box 1)
    - Blodget, Harold (Box 1)
    - Blotner, Joseph (Box 1)
    - Boatright, Mody (Box 1)
    - Bode, Carl (Box 1)
    - Boewe, Charles (Box 1)
    - Boorstin, Daniel (Box 1)
    - Bond, Richmond P. (Box 1)
    - Bowers, Fredson (Box 1)
    - Bowling, Lawrence (Box 1)
    - Boyce, Benjamin (Box 1)
    - Brack, O. M. (Box 1)
    - Braddy, Haldeen (Box 1)
    - Bradley, Phil (Box 1)
    - Bradley, Scully (Box 1)
    - Brice, Ashbel (Box 1)
    - Broderick, John C. (Box 1)
    - Brown, Herbert (Box 1)
    - Browne, Ray B. (Box 1)
    - Bruccoli, Matthew (Box 1)
    - Bryant, Joe (Box 1)
    - Budd, Louis (Box 1)
    - Butcher, Philip (Box 1)
    - Byers, John (Box 1)
    - B Misc. (Box 1)
    - Cady, Edwin Harrison (Box 2)
    - Cameron, Kenneth (Box 2)
    - Cantwell, Robert (Box 2)
    - Cardwell, Guy (Box 2)
    - Carson, Patricia (Box 2)
    - Carroll, Martin (Box 2)
    - Cherry, Kenneth (Box 2)
    - Cline, Clarence L. (Box 2)
    - Clogan, Paul (Box 2)
    - Cohen, Bernard (Box 2)
    - Cohen, Hennig (Box 2)
    - Cole, R. Taylor (Box 2)
    - Collins, Carvel (Box 2)
    - Colvert, James (Box 2)
    - Cone, Eddie G. and Roberta L. (Box 2)
    - Corbett, Joan (Box 2)
    - Core, George (Box 2)
    - Covici, Pascal (Box 2)
    - Crawley, T. Edward (Box 2)
    - Crowley, J. Donald (Box 2)
    - Curlee, Roy (Box 2)
    - Current-Garcia, Gene (Box 2)
    - C Misc. (Box 2)
    - Dainow, Joseph (Box 2)
    - Dalton, Harry L. (Box 2)
    - Davidson, Edward (Box 2)
    - Davis, Charles T. (Box 2)
    - Davis, Curtis Carroll (Box 2)
    - Davison, Kenneth E. (Box 2)
    - Dedmond, Francis B. (Box 2)
    - Demanuelli, Jean (Box 2)
    - Dembo, L. S. (Box 2)
    - Denbo, Bruce F. (Box 2)
    - Dickey, James (Box 2)
    - Donaldson, Scott (Box 2)
    - Dorris, George (Box 2)
    - Dos Passos, John (Box 2)
    - Downey, Harris (Box 2)
    - Duban, James (Box 2)
    - Dykeman (Stokely), Wilma (Box 2)
    - D Misc. (Box 2)
    - Engle, Paul (Box 2)
    - Erdman, Loula Grace (Box 2)
    - Ervine, Roberta (Box 2)
    - Estes, David (Box 2)
    - Fisher, Benjamin Franklin (Box 2)
    - Freeman, Gordon (Box 2)
    - Foerster, Norman (Box 2)
    - Hartle, Anthony E. (Box 3)
    - Hersey, John (Box 3)
    - Hoffman, Daniel (Box 3)
    - Hoffman, Frederick (Box 3)
    - Hornberger, Theodore (Box 3)
    - Howarth, R. Guy (Box 3)
    - Hubbell, Jay B. (Box 3)
    - Hughes, Rupert (Box 3)
    - H Misc. (Box 3)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford (Box 3)
    - Jones, Joseph (Box 3)
    - Jones, Tandy (Box 3)
    - King, Alec (Box 3)
    - Knickerbocker, William S. (Box 3)
    - K Misc. (Box 3)
    - Leary, Lewis (Box 3)
    - Liljegren, Sten Bodvar (Box 3)
    - Ljungquist, Kent (Box 3)
    - Lovelace, Joseph (Box 3)
    - L Misc. (Box 3)
    - Mabbott, Thomas Ollive (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, F. O. (Box 3)
    - Mays, James O. (Box 3)
    - McDavid, Raven I. (Box 3)
    - Michener, James A. (Box 3)
    - Mordell, Albert (Box 3)
    - M Misc. (Box 3)
    - O'Brien, Claudine (Box 3)
    - Osborn, Scott (Box 3)
    - Owen, Guy (Box 3)
    - O Misc. (Box 3)
    - Parkinson, Thomas (Box 3)
    - Pearson, Norman H. (Box 3)
    - Poirier, Richard (Box 3)
    - Pond, James B. (Box 3)
    - Porter, Katherine Anne (Box 3)
    - Price, Reynolds (Box 3)
    - P. Misc. (Box 3)
    - Rak, Mary Kidder (Box 3)
    - Ransom, Harry Huntt (Box 3)
    - Ransom, John Crowe (Box 3)
    - Reeves, Paschal (Box 3)
    - Reid, Alfred S. (Box 3)
    - Rosenthal, Mack K. (Box 3)
    - R Misc. (Box 3)
    - Schorer, Mark (Box 3)
    - Simpson, Claude M. (Box 3)
    - Stafford, William (Box 3)
    - Stephenson, Wendell H. (Box 3)
    - Stevens, George (Box 3)
    - Stewart, Randall (Box 3)
    - Stovall, Floyd (Box 3)
    - Stuart, Jesse (Box 3)
    - S Misc. (Box 3)
    - Thompson, Lawrence (Box 3)
    - Tinker, Edward Larocque (Box 3)
    - T Misc. (Box 3)
    - Waite, Mary Abbott (Box 3)
    - Ward, Charles E. (Box 3)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 3)
    - Weaver, Richard M. (Box 3)
    - Wecter, Dixon (Box 3)
    - Welland, Dennis (Box 3)
    - Wilson, Edmund (Box 3)
    - Woll, Harvey (Box 3)
    - W Misc. (Box 3)
    - Yeatman, Joan (Box 3)
    - Unidentified (Box 3)
  - Publications Subseries, 1934-1979
    The Publications Subseries is comprised of Turner's correspondence to publishers, editors, and presses regarding publications. Included are reviews of books for multiple journals, multiple reviews written for single journals, manuscript evaluations for various university presses, and correspondence regarding some of Turner's own publications. Arranged alphabetically by publication title or press name.
    - American Literature: An Anthology (Box 4)
    - American Quarterly (Box 4)
    - Australian Literary Studies (Box 4)
    - Clio (Box 4)
    - Dictionary of Literary Biography (Box 4)
    - Duke University Press (Box 4)
    - Editors' News (Box 4)
    - Faulkner: A Biography by Blotner (Box 4)
    - Harvard University Press (Box 4)
    - (Washington) Irving Edition (Box 4)